{"tossups": [{"question": "Nedeljko Cabrinovic tried to accomplish this act with a bombing earlier in the day. The July Ultimatum was sent in response to this event, which was planned by the (*) Black Hand, a pro-Serbian group. For ten points, name this June 28, 1914 event in which Gavrilo Princip killed an Austro-Hungarian royal, triggering World War I.", "answer": "assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand (accept terms like \"killing\" or \"shooting\" instead of \"assassination;\" do not accept or prompt partial name)", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The majority of these animals are passerines, and have a backward-facing toe. These organisms evolved independently of mammals, but they are still endothermic vertebrates with four-chambered hearts. Unlike their ancestor (*) Archaeopteryx, these animals lack teeth. Hard eggs and light skeletons are characteristics of, for ten points, what class of feathered animals that includes the flightless ostrich?", "answer": "birds (accept Aves)", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Sierpinski's triangle is a fractal image created by shading this diagram's even numbers. Tthe calculation \"n choose k\" will find the kth number in its nth row, and this diagram's rows list the (*) binomial coefficients. A French mathematician names, for ten points, what expanding mathematical image whose first few rows are \"1\", then \"1,1\", then \"1,2,1\"?", "answer": "Pascal's triangle", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In Chinese mythology, Dian Mu used these objects to throw her lightning bolts. The Shinto goddess Amaterasu \ufffcwas lured out of a cave by one of these objects, which showed her brilliance. The Aztec god Tezcatlipoca was represented as a \"smoking\" one of these objects, and (*)) Perseus used a shield as one of these objects to freeze Medusa with her own gaze. For ten points, name these reflective surfaces.", "answer": "mirrors", "subcategory": "Mythology Other", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This state's popular dueling site, Weehawken, was where both Philip and Alexander Hamilton were fatally shot. Hessian forces were attacked on (*) Christmas Day in this state, after George Washington crossed the Delaware into this state to start the Battle of Trenton. For ten points, name this state in which American forces won the Battle of Princeton.", "answer": "New Jersey", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This novel's title character battles the Knight of the White Moon, and is forced to cease all acts of chivalry for a year. This work's title character tries to save the \"princess\" Dulcinea with the help of his squire, (*) Sancho Panza, and rides the elderly steed, Rocinante. For ten points, name this novel about a windmill-dueling, delusional \"knight,\" written by Miguel de Cervantes.", "answer": "The Ingenious Gentleman Don Quijote of La Mancha (accept El ingenioso hidalgo don Quijote de La Mancha)", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The theory of special relativity uses reference frames to explain one of these statements involving an astronaut twin. These concepts often arise from thought experiments, such as a time traveler killing his own ancestor. The phrase \"this phrase is (*) false\" is an example of these statements, because it cannot seem to be true or false. For ten points, name this type of confusing statement or argument, which logically contradicts itself.", "answer": "paradox (accept word forms, like paradoxical statement; prompt on descriptions, like self- contradiction, before said)", "subcategory": "Philosophy Other", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "While investigating this event, Luis Alvarez discovered that sediment from around the world displays a layer of iridium dating to this event. This event may have begun at Chicxulub \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc on the Yucatan peninsula, and ended the (*) Mesozoic Era. A meteor may have caused, for ten points, what devastating event 65 million years ago that wiped out thousands of species, including T. Rex?", "answer": "extinction of the dinosaurs (accept K-T extinction event or Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction event; accept K-Pg extinction or Cretaceous-Paleogene extinction)", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The first president of this country instituted \"Harambee,\" a community-building strategy. Dedan Kimathi led an uprising in the 1950s that sought to reclaim Kikuyu land from European colonists. The (*) Mau Mau Rebellion challenged British rule of, for ten points, what African country with capital Nairobi, first led by Jomo Kenyatta?", "answer": "Republic of Kenya", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A poem in this format by Elizabeth Barrett Browning asks \"How do I love thee? Let me count the ways,\" and is collected in \"these poems\" from the Portuguese. An (*) Elizabethan version of this poetic form is composed of three quatrains and a couplet. \"Shall I compare thee to a summer's day?\" is a poem in this format written by Shakespeare. For ten points, name these fourteen-line poems.", "answer": "sonnets", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One of these instruments is played by Tamino to change sorrow into joy while he tries to save Pamina from Sarastro. In an opera named for one of these instruments, \"Der Holle Rache\" \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc is sung by the (*) Queen of the Night. For ten points, name this woodwind instrument, the Magic subject of a Mozart opera, whose smaller relatives include the piccolo.", "answer": "flute (accept The Magic Flute or Die Zauberflo \u0308te)", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This state's \"Unassigned Lands\" were claimed in an infamous 1889 land rush. In this state's capital, 168 people were killed in a 1995 bombing by Timothy McVeigh. In 1921, the wealthiest African-American community in the country, the Greenwood district, was burned during this state's (*) Tulsa race riots. For ten points, name this central U.S. state where \"Sooners\" now live in a panhandle north of Texas.", "answer": "Oklahoma", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The wirewound type of this device produces undesired inductance. The total effect of a system of these devices is found by summing of the reciprocals of their strengths if they are connected in (*) parallel; the effect is additive instead if they are in series. The strength of these circuit elements is marked with colored bands. For ten points, name this circuit element that inhibits the flow of electrical current and whose strength is measured in Ohms.", "answer": "resistors", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Six Miqats \ufffcare stations on the way to this city. This city is visited during the Umrah, and believers in this city walk in circles around this city's (*)) Ka'aba to remember its construction by Ismail and Ibrahim. All able-bodied Muslims must at some point in their life complete the Hajj, a pilgrimage to, for ten points, what holy Saudi city?", "answer": "Mecca", "subcategory": "Religion Islam", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A local ruler in this book possesses a Golden Cap that can summon an army three times, and is too afraid of water to steal the Silver Shoes, which this novel's protagonist uses to return to her (*) Aunt Em, with Glinda's help. For ten points, name this L. Frank Baum novel Dorothy follows the yellow brick road in hopes of meeting the title figure.", "answer": "The Wonderful Wizard of Oz (accept The Wizard of Oz, since the novel has occasionally been reprinted under that title)", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "A music video for this album begins with the voiceover \"I tried to change\" and the caption \"Denial.\" Another song from this album was criticized as \"anti-police\" after it was performed at Super Bowl (*) 50's halftime show. Another song on this album ends \"He better call Becky with the good hair.\" For ten points, name this 2016 album, featuring the singles \"Hold Up,\" \"Formation,\" and \"Sorry,\" by Beyonce \u0301.", "answer": "Lemonade", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This architect's \"inverted ziggurat\" is a feature of his design for a building with a spiraling interior walkway, the Guggenheim Museum in New York. This man extended (*) cantilevered floors over Bear Run, a stream in Pennsylvania, in creating a house for the Kaufmann family. For ten points, name this Prairie School architect of Fallingwater.", "answer": "Frank Lloyd Wright (accept Frank Lincoln Wright)", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This city is home to the port town of Jebel Ali, a top-10 port in the world southwest of the Strait of Hormuz. Housing in this city is built on artificial, palm-frond-shaped landmasses that sit along the (*) Persian Gulf north of Abu Dhabi. For ten points, name this most populous city in the United Arab Emirates, the home of the world's tallest building, the Burj Khalifa.", "answer": "Dubai", "subcategory": "Geography World", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "This work's title character claims that the \"Indians of Cleveland\" will be defeated by The Great DiMaggio, and goes for eighty-four days without a catch before he hooks a giant marlin without (*) Manolin's help. The title fisherman's catch is eaten by sharks on the way back to Cuba in, for ten points, what novella about the elderly fisherman Santiago, written by Ernest Hemingway?", "answer": "The Old Man and the Sea", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "These phenomena are used to observe diffraction patterns in the Advanced Photon Source. Rosalind Franklin scattered this type of radiation to take (*) images of DNA. This type of radiation has energy output just less than that of gamma rays. For ten points, name this type of electromagnetic radiation commonly used in medical imaging to view teeth and bones.", "answer": "x-rays", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}], "bonuses": []}